原视频名：The Unluckiest Satellites - Earthquakes, Rockets and Clogged Pipes
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/IxyT__Vcw0k
原视频发布日期：20210322
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Today I want to talk to you about a series of unfortunate rocket failures
今天我想跟大家说的是一系列倒霉的火箭事故
which were all linked together into a larger narrative of accidents poor choices
这一切错误而意外的选择都连成了一系列更大的不幸事件
and simple bad luck for everybody involved.
而与之相关的每个人都很倒霉
Our story starts out with a communication satellite named Superbird-B or Superbird-2.
我们的故事从一颗名为超级鸟-B或超级鸟-2的通信卫星开始
This was intended to deliver satellite TV from a slot above the eastern pacific.
这颗卫星的目的是为了在东太平洋上空提供卫星电视服务
It was a two-and-a-half ton spacecraft built by Ford aerospace.
这是一个重达两吨半的航天器 由福特航天公司制造
Yes Ford used to build satellites.
是的 福特公司曾经制造过卫星
It was being built at a facility in Palo Alto California in 1989
1989年 它在加州帕洛阿尔托的一个工厂中被制造出来
with a plan to launch on the relatively new Ariane 4 rocket which had debuted the previous year.
并计划用前一年首次亮相的比较新的阿丽亚娜4号火箭发射
And allowed the final flight to Ariane two and three in 1989.
阿丽亚娜4号的出现让阿丽亚娜2号和3号火箭在1989年进行了最后的飞行
Now if you were in Palo Alto in 1989 there was one big event you probably remembered.
那么如果你1989年在帕洛阿尔托 你可能记得一件大事
On october 17th the Loma Prieta earthquake struck the bay area causing damage all over the place.
在10月17日 洛马·普雷塔地震袭击了海湾地区 对各地造成了破坏
This was a decade before I started living here
我十年后才开始住在这里
but my wife remembers the quake and its aftermath well and talks about it often.
但我妻子对地震及其后果记得很清楚 经常说起
Now the quake caused minor damage to the satellite
那么 地震对卫星造成了轻微的损坏
which meant that it wasn't going to be ready in time for its planned launch
这意味着它无法在计划中的发射时间内准备好
and this was somewhat problematic because it was going to share a launch with another satellite called BS2X
这造成了一点麻烦 因为它将与另一颗名为BS2X的卫星共用一次发射
which would have to then wait.
那它就得再等等了
But for Arianespace they had another payload that was ready to go sooner the French SPOT 2 satellite
但对于阿丽亚娜空间来说 他们还有另一个有效载荷可以更快地进行发射 法国的SPOT 2卫星
and it also was with a number of other small amateur radio satellites.
而且还有其他一些小型业余无线电卫星
So they took this payload and reassigned the booster that was assigned to Superbird and gave it to SPOT 2.
所以他们把这个有效载荷 以及之前分配给超级鸟的火箭重新分配给了SPOT 2号
And this mission then launched in January of 1990.
而这个任务就在1990年1月发射了
Then in February a month later both communication satellites were mated on top of an Ariane 4
一个月后的2月 两颗通信卫星都在阿丽亚娜4号的顶部进行了安装
which needed four extra strap-on liquid boosters
它需要额外四个捆绑式液体助推器
so that it would be able to reach the required geostationary transfer orbit.
以便达到所需的地球静止转移轨道
Countdown went as planned but as the vehicle began to rise up off the pad
倒计时按计划进行 但当火箭开始上升离开发射台时
the temperatures in one of the engines turbines rapidly exceeded operating limits.
其中一台发动机的涡轮的温度迅速超过了工作极限
The thrust dropped off and very quickly the engine essentially shut down
推力下降 而发动机很快就基本关闭了
and you can actually see this missing engine in this video of the launch.
而且 实际上你可以在这个发射视频里看到这台熄火的发动机
You can see the missing exhaust
你可以看到缺失的废气
and as the rocket moves up
而当火箭移动起来时
it starts to slip sideways coming really close to the launch tower.
它开始向侧面滑动 并靠近发射塔
We actually see the rocket exhaust blasting the top of that tower.
实际上 我们可以看到火箭的废气吹到了发射塔的顶部
Now that missing engine meant that it lost one 8th of the normal thrust
那么 熄火的发动机意味着它失去了正常推力的八分之一
but actually still had enough thrust to weight ratio to lift it up
但实际上仍有足够的推重比将其推动
and let it ascend and accelerate up towards supersonic speeds.
并让它上升并加速到超音速
But I think at this point engineers and mission control didn't think there was much hope of this vehicle reaching orbit
但我想 在这时 工程师和任务控制部门并不认为这个航天器还有希望入轨
but it might at least get far enough away from the launch sites
但它至少可以远离发射场
that it didn't dump debris and those toxic hypergolic propellants all over the place.
这样火箭残骸和那些有毒的自燃推进剂就不会掉在发射场里
While it had enough thrust to fly, it didn't really have the control authority.
虽然它有足够的推力来飞行 但它并没有足够的能力去控制姿态
The Ariane 4 has four engines each on a single axis gimbal
阿丽亚娜4号有四台发动机 每台发动机都安装在一个单向摆动轴上
and with one engine missing it actually lost one degree of freedom and of its control.
而它少了一台发动机 实际上失去了一个自由度的控制权
And also with the off-center thrust the engine control system was trying to counteract this
而且由于推力偏离中心 发动机控制系统正试图抵消它
and it did so for about a minute or so before it eventually exceeded those capabilities
而且控制系统最终控制了一分多钟左右
and the vehicle lost control and was torn apart by aerodynamic forces scattering debris over the nearby wetlands.
然后火箭失控 被气动力撕碎 残骸散落在附近的湿地上
But thankfully most of the toxic propellant burned during that breakup.
但值得庆幸的是 大部分的有毒推进剂在那次破裂中烧完了
For the next few days the French foreign legion would be tramping through the swampy terrain
在接下来的几天里 法国外籍军团将在沼泽地里踯躅前行
collecting debris that might give them some clue as to what went wrong.
收集可能会给他们提供一些线索的残骸 以确定事故问题
In the end they found the smoking gun in a section of piping from a Viking engine
最后 他们在一段维京发动机的管道里找到了罪魁祸首
which had some cloth stuffed into it.
里面塞了一些布料
That wasn't supposed to be here.
而这不应该出现在这里
The Viking engine uses hypergolic propellants fed by a turbo pump
维京发动机的自燃推进剂由涡轮泵输送
and the pump is driven by burning some fuel and oxidizer in a gas generator
而泵由燃烧一些燃料和氧化剂的气体发生器来驱动
and using the exhaust from that to drive the turbines.
而气体发射器里的涡轮由燃烧产生的废气来驱动
维京发动机的气体发生器
燃料和氧化剂从顶部注入，产生高温燃烧
底部喷水，来给废气降温
因为使用了理想混合比，参考youtu.be/DFbzvbkoEYs?t=175
But on its own that exhaust gas would be too hot for the turbines.
但只是使用废气 对涡轮来说太热了
So they're cooled by spraying water into that exhaust so the temperature drops.
所以他们通过向废气中喷水来冷却 这样温度就降低了
Now the cloth in that pipe was blocking the water flow
那么管道里的布挡住了水的流动
which meant the turbine very quickly overheated and didn't perform thus killing the engine.
这意味着涡轮机很快就过热了 不能正常工作 从而导致发动机故障
I guess the fact that it was in a water pipe
我觉得实际上 这块布是在一根水管里
meant that it protected it against burning with all the flammable propellants
这样水就可以保护它不被易燃推进剂烧掉
and that's how they were able to find this afterwards.
这样他们才会在事故后找到它
The story about how the cloth got in there.
而关于布是如何进入那里的
Well I hear that was a technician that was working on connecting some plumbing that he'd had some trouble with
我听说是一个技术员在连接一些管道时出了点问题
so he'd like re-polished it and got it to fit.
所以他想把管道重新抛光 让它能装上去
But he needed a supervisor to approve of this.
但他需要一个主管的批准
So apparently he left his handkerchief in there.
那么很明显 他把他的手帕落在那里了
It was a friday night there were no supervisors around so we went home for the weekend.
那是个周五的晚上 周围没有主管 所以技术员回家去过周末了
And got sick.
然后就生病了
So somebody else came in monday morning and completed the job that he had started
那么有人在周一早上来完成了他之前进行的工作
not noticing that there was a piece of cloth in this pipe.
没有注意到这根管子里有一块布
A cloth of doom as you might say.
你可以说是一块倒霉的布
So yes I'm not sure how truthful that is
那么是的 我不知道这个段子有多真实
but I do believe it when I hear that these days when they're making engines
但我确实相信 当我听说 现在他们制造发动机的时候
they keep track of every single cloth by giving it a serial number.
会给每一块布编号来进行追踪
So look it was a terrible bit of bad luck for Superbird which survived an earthquake
那么你看 对于在地震中幸存下来的超级鸟来说 这是非常倒霉的
only to have its launch vehicle switched to one with a fatal flaw.
(等待)换来的却是有致命缺陷的运载火箭
On the other hand it was a stroke of luck for Arianespace
另一方面 对阿丽亚娜空间来说 这也是一种幸运
since the SPOT 2 spacecraft was originally designated to fly on the doomed booster
因为SPOT 2航天器最初是被指定在注定要失败的助推器上飞行的
because it was a smaller payload and going to a lower orbit
因为它是一个质量较小的有效载荷 而且进入的轨道较低
it wouldn't need those strap-on boosters.
就不需要那些捆绑式助推器
So if that had flown with the failed engine
所以 如果它使用带有故障的发动机的芯一级火箭发射的话
it would have only had three working engines instead of seven
就只有三台发动机能正常工作 而不是捆绑式助推器情况下的七台
and the crash would have probably happened right on the pad
而火箭的坠毁很可能就会在发射台上发生
probably causing serious damage and a major cleanup situation with all the toxic propellant.
可能会造成严重的破坏 同时需要大规模清理有毒推进剂
But that is not the end of this story because Superbird's partner on this launch was another satellite called BS2X.
但这还不是这个故事的结尾 因为超级鸟在这次发射中的拼车卫星是另一颗名为BS2X的卫星
And again that was another communication satellite.
这也是一颗通信卫星
The operator of course had built two of these
当然 运营方已经建造了两颗这样的卫星
because it was quite common practice to have a backup satellite ready to go
因为准备一颗备用卫星是很常见的做法
in case of a launch problem like this.
以防出现这样的发射问题
After their unfortunate experience with Ariane
在经历了阿丽亚娜的不幸之后
the satellite operator decided that they would switch over to an Atlas-Centaur launch vehicle
卫星运营方决定改用宇宙神-半人马运载火箭
a rocket which was returning to the fore
一枚正在再上岗的火箭
as it became clear that the Space Shuttle was never going to be commercially viable.
因为很明显 航天飞机在商业发射上是不可行的
In april of 1991, Atlas AC-70 launched with the payload and it performed admirably
1991年4月 宇宙神AC-70携带有效载荷发射 它的表现相当不错
dropping its booster engines and then later releasing the Centaur upper stage.
分离了助推器发动机 后来又释放了半人马上面级
But historically reliable Centaur suffered a problem with one of its engines failing to ignite and operate
但历史上可靠的半人马遭遇了一台发动机无法点火和运行的问题
and the other ended up spinning the stage out of control until it was destroyed by the flight termination system.
而另一台则使二级旋转并失控 然后被飞行终止系统摧毁
An investigation was started right away but they didn't have any recovered hardware to investigate.
调查立刻开始进行 但他们没有找到任何设备来进行调查
They did have telemetry showed that showing the turbo pump didn't speed up like it was supposed to.
确实有遥测数据显示 涡轮泵没有像它应该的那样加速
So they looked at the turbine inlet and the plumbing around the engines
所以他们检查了涡轮进气口和发动机周围的管道
and they did find something that they thought was problematic.
他们确实发现了一些认为有问题的东西
So the turbines they basically work like a high precision windmill.
那么涡轮的工作原理基本上就像一个高精度的风车
You blow fluid over the spinning structure that spins it
你把流体吹到旋转的结构上 使其旋转起来
and it's in a pipe where the blades go right up against the edge.
而且管道内部的涡轮叶片紧贴着管道内部边缘
And you want that gap between the blades and the edge of the pipe to be as tight as possible
你要让涡轮叶片和管道边缘之间的缝隙尽可能的紧密
because any gap means that you're losing efficiency
因为任何多余的缝隙都意味着你的效率在下降
and of course touching the walls means you've got extra friction.
而当然 (没有缝隙)接触内壁意味着你有额外的摩擦力
But anything that can get stuck in that tiny gap can be a real drag
但任何卡在那个缝隙里的东西 就会真的变成阻力
and that's really important in the RL-10 engines
而这在RL-10发动机中是非常重要的
because they have a very slow startup.
因为其启动非常缓慢
Because they sort of rely on waste engine heat to boil hydrogen so they can drive those pumps.
这差不多是因为(膨胀循环)依靠发动机的废热来加热液氢到沸点 才能驱动这些泵
so it doesn't take much friction in those turbines to slow or arrest the startup completely.
那么在涡轮上 并不需要太多的摩擦力就会减慢启动速度 甚至会完全停止启动
So the engineers examined the engine fresh out of the factory
那么工程师们对刚出厂的发动机进行了检查
and they found tiny fragments of plastic from scouring pads which were being used to clean the plumbing.
而他们发现了微小的塑料碎片 这些碎片来自用于清洁管道的擦洗垫上
And they concluded that these fragments had caused enough drag to stall the engine as it tried to start up.
于是他们得出结论 这些碎片造成了足够的阻力 使发动机在试图启动时熄火
So the engine production procedures were then modified to require baking of all this plumbing
于是 他们修改了发动机的生产程序 要求对所有这些管道进行烘烤
hot enough to burn out any of the plastic fragments that might cause this problem.
温度高到烧掉任何可能导致这一问题的塑料碎片
Confident in their solution they prepared for the next launch.
而他们对自己的解决方案充满信心 准备进行下一次发射
Over a year later in August of 1992 this time it was carrying a Hughes Galaxy 1R satellite.
一年多后的1992年8月 这次发射的是休斯公司的银河1R卫星
Again the booster performed admirably and once again the Centaur had one engine fail
同样地 一级火箭的表现非常不错 而半人马座上面级再次出现了一台发动机故障
with the turbo pump failing to spin up and the payload was lost.
涡轮泵无法旋转起来 之后损失了有效载荷
This was pretty embarrassing.
这是相当尴尬的
Exactly the same failure.
故障一模一样
The original investigation had come to the wrong conclusion.
原来的调查得出了错误的结论
Initially they couldn't replicate the failed startup on the ground
最初他们无法在地面上复现启动失败的情况
It would take a stroke of luck to give them the insight needed
运气好的话 他们才能搞清楚发生了什么
One day having prepared the engine for a test run, the team broke for lunch.
有一天 在准备好要测试发动机后 团队休息 去吃午饭了
And when they came back they replicated the failure to start.
当他们回来的时候 他们就复现了启动失败的情况
What had been happening
这里发生的事情是
was that the engine chill down system would run cold helium through some parts of the engine
发动机冷却系统在发动机的某些部分中通过冷氦气
to prepare it for the really cold liquid hydrogen.
为真正寒冷的液氢做准备
This helium would exhaust out through one-way check valves
这些氦气会通过单向止回阀排出
but it turns out that these one-way valves weren't quite as one-way as expected under the operating conditions.
但事实证明 这些单向阀在特定的工作条件下并不像预期的那样起作用
So air would actually leak back in through these check valves and that air would liquefy at the temperature.
那么空气实际上会通过这些单向阀泄漏回来 而这些空气会在这样的温度下液化
In fact at the temperature of liquid hydrogen it could solidify and form nitrogen and oxygen ice.
事实上 在液氢的温度下 空气会凝固并形成固态氮和固态氧
Not a lot but enough to jam up the turbine.
虽然不会很多 但足以卡住涡轮
So the solution was then to replace the valves with better ones
所以解决的办法就是换上更好的阀门
which could stop backflow of air into the system.
可以阻止空气倒流进入系统
Oroblem solved then right. Sure.
问题解决了吧 好了吧
It's just a shame that the next Atlas launch after that would also be a failure for a completely unrelated reason.
只是很可惜 之后的下一次宇宙神发射也会因为完全不相关的原因而失败
A loose screw which resulted in the main engine underperforming
一个松动的螺丝 导致主发动机性能不佳
but since then Atlas had had a near perfect launch record.
但从那时起 宇宙神的发射记录近乎完美
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]